Guide to the Jessie F. Wheeler Papers, 1852-1929
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Jessie F. Wheeler Papers
1852-1929
Wheeler, Jessie F., 1858-1946
0.4 cubic feet (2 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Scrapbooks, logbooks, album, diploma, and daguerreotypes, primarily concerning Wheeler's family. Other items include programs from Vassar College events, 1878-1879.
Biographical Note
Jessie F. Wheeler, born in Saratoga County, NY, and graduated from Vassar College in 1882. She attended the New York State Library School in 1903 and was reference librarian at the Troy Public Library for approximately eighteen years. Miss Wheeler, a resident of Mechanicville, NY, enjoyed traveling and raising trees from seed. She had a deep interest in local history and genealogy, wrote many historical articles, and was a leading organizer of the Saratoga Battlefield Sesqui-Centennial Celebration in 1927. For forty years she collected information on Samuel Wilson of Troy, reputed to have been the original "Uncle Sam." A recluse in her later years, Miss Wheeler gave many books to the Vassar Library and established the Jessie F. Wheeler Vassar College Library Fund.
Scope and Content Note
Papers primarily concerning Wheeler's family, including two scrapbooks of genealogical material; logbooks, 1925-1929; an album and diploma of her mother Agnes Gould Wheeler from Galway Ladies Seminary, 1852-1854; and daguerreotypes of her parents Charles and Agnes Wheeler. Other items include programs from Vassar College events, 1878-1879.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
See also the papers of Wheeler's classmates:
Sutematsu Yamakawa Oyama
Shige Nagai Uriu
Separated Materials
A scrapbook, photo album, and some school notes were added to the VC Student Materials collection at an unknown date.
Student Materials guide
Subject Headings
Names:
Wheeler, Agnes Gould; Wheeler, Charles; Wheeler family
Organizations:
Galway Ladies' Seminary; Vassar College--Students
Subjects:
Women college students--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie
Document Types:
Genealogies; Daguerreotypes; Scrapbooks
VCL Categories
Family; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, August 2007.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Jessie F. Wheeler.
Container List
- Vassar College music programs, 1878-1889 (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks containing genealogical material about Jessie Wheeler’s family, (2 volumes) (Box 1)
- Logbook, 1925-1929 (Box 1)
- Logbook, 1925-1929 (Box 2)
- Logbook, 1925-1929 (Box 2)
- Agnes Gould Wheeler's album — Galway Ladies’ Seminary, 1852-1854 (Box 2)
- Agnes Gould Wheeler's Diploma from the Galway Ladies’ Seminary, 1854 (Box 2)
- Daguerreotype of Agnes Gould Wheeler in graduation gown, 1854 (Box 2)
- Daguerreotype of Charles Wheeler (Box 2)
- Daguerreotype of Charles Wheeler and Agnes Gould Wheeler taken on their wedding trip (Box 2)
- Sampler giving the genealogy of the Clitz family (Box 2)
- Album of trade cards (Box 2)